While my little brother, Nanba Hibito, prepares to become the first Japanese person to walk on the moon,
なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜日本人で初めて
月面に立つ我が弟➡
ひびと
南波日々人を追って
宇宙飛行士試験に挑む私➡
I, Nanba Mutta,
兄 南波六太は アメリカ
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡで行う最終面接に➡
manage to survive the final interview, at NASA, for the astronaut selection exam.
ギリギリで こぎつけた＞
After coming this far, I'm practically an astronaut!
＜ここまでくれば
宇宙飛行士になったも同然➡
Or so I thought,
と思いきや
怪し～い空気が漂い始めていた＞
but something felt wrong.
Anyway, I have another present from Mom.
それより 今回も母ちゃんから
お土産があるぞ｡
まさか…賞味期限ギリギリの
キムチとか？
More kimchi that's about to expire?
イエス
ＹＥＳ！
Yes!
(オジー)危ないぞ ムッタ！
Look out, Mutta!
油断したらダメよ あんた｡➡
But you need to be extra careful.
あんたにとっては
それが一番 難関かもよ｡➡
The final exam could be your biggest challenge.
本来なら順番的に アズマが先に
月に立つはずでしょ？➡
In terms of seniority, Azuma should have been the first one to step on the moon.
だから アズマはヒビトのことを
ねた
妬んでるってワケよ｡
So Azuma bears a grudge against Hibito.
ほしか
(星加)ＮＡＳＡでの最終面接は
フェイクだ｡➡
The final interview held at NASA is a decoy.
これで全て終わったと
思わせること｡➡
The objective is to convince the candidates that they're done.
Right now, they're letting loose and relaxing, while being carefully monitored.
今頃 肩の荷が下りきって➡
素に近い受験者達が 事細かに
チェックされてるはずだ｡
みやた
むらさき
(宮田)紫 お前 南波君に➡
Murasaki, you told Nanba to stay away from Azuma?
あずま
吾妻さんには
話しかけるなとか言ってたろ｡
Oh, you heard that?
(紫)あ 聞こえてた？ワリィ｡
Sorry.
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)あんたが不利な理由は➡
And you're at a disadvantage
because Azuma is an evaluator.
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡの最終試験の審査員に
そのアズマがいるってことよ｡
I felt bad because he's in a bad position, so I wanted to help.
つい 不利なアイツが
かわいそ～に思えてさ➡
なんか軽く
助け船 出しちゃった｡
I get where you're coming from, but it had the opposite effect.
(宮田)気持ちは わかるが
どうやら逆効果だぞ｡
(紫)《うわっ…
バカか!?南波六太！》
Are you stupid, Nanba Mutta?!
Seven Days
Space Brothers
Before my uneasiness
was the end
of my happiness
I came to you
and we were one
Hello Hello
Let's fly
Here in this world we dream
and keep on dancing
Here among light and shadow
we keep changing
so that the wind doesn't let up
Even though the future is vague and unreliable
we are
not alone
#27 One Question
Houston,
(通信:吾妻の声)ヒューストン
こちら アズマ｡➡
this is Azuma.
The CMG has been replaced.
シーエムジー
ＣＭＧの交換工事完了｡
余った時間で➡
I intend to use the remaining time to repair the solar panels.
太陽電池パネルの
補修工事でもやるが 問題ないか？
Any objections?
(職員)サンキュー アズマ｡
それは大いに助かるが➡
Thanks, Azuma.
We appreciate the thought, but you've managed to put us ahead of schedule.
君のおかげで
時間に余裕ができたよ｡➡
少し休んで
地球でも眺めたら どうだい？
Why not just enjoy the view?
Roger.
(通信:吾妻の声)了解｡
驚いたな｡他のクルーの
倍の作業効率だぞ｡
I'm impressed...
He works twice as fast as the other crew members.
アハハハ これから
アズマの加わるミッションには➡
When he's sent on a mission, we'll need a special manual for him.
彼専用のマニュアルが必要だな｡
全くその通りだな｡
You're absolutely right.
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)《素晴らしい！➡
Marvelous.
フッ…アズマ･タキオか》
Azuma Takio...
アズマ
地球の様子は どうだい？
Azuma, tell us how Earth looks.
Consider this your speech rehearsal.
スピーチの練習代わりに
何かコメントくれよ｡
おいおい アズマに
こく
そこまで求めんのは 酷だろう｡
Hey, it's cruel to ask Azuma that.
He isn't big on public speaking.
そういうの苦手なんだから｡
(通信:吾妻の声)ヒューストン｡
申し訳ないが➡
Houston.
My apologies.
これを表現するには…｡
But this view I have...
言葉じゃ足りない｡
Words cannot describe it.
Excuse me.
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)ちょっと失礼｡
あっ ブライアン｡
《うわ～大御所来たぁ…》
Brian!
The big guy's here...
アズマ…
こちらブライアン･Ｊだ｡➡
Azuma, this is Brian Jay.
見てたよ 君の働き｡
I was watching you in action.
は はじめまして｡
I-It's an honor.
《本物…!?》
It's really him?
気分のいいところ悪いが➡
I'm sorry to interrupt.
But I had a stupid question for you.
１コだけ
くだらねぇ質問に答えてくれ｡
死ぬ覚悟ってある？
Are you prepared to die?
現在
Okay, I'm going to talk to him.
《よし…ズバッと言ってやる！》
Are you worried about Azuma, Nanba?
⦅吾妻さんが気になるのか？
南波君⦆
Huh? No...
⦅ん…いや
怒ってんのかな～と思って⦆
I just wondered if he's mad.
He isn't mad. He always looks that way.
(紫)⦅怒ってないよ｡
あれが普通なの｡➡
That's his neutral face.
ニュートラルフェイス｡
つっても俺も怖いけど｡➡
But honestly, it scares me, too.
まあ 彼と仲良くなろう
ってのはムリだな｡➡
Well, you won't be able to make friends with him.
チームワークは大事にするけど
｢友達｣って関係には➡
He values teamwork, but he's not big on friendship.
なろうとしない人だ｡
俺やミヤッチでもな｡➡
Not even with Miya-chi or me.
彼には むやみに
話しかけない方がいいかもな⦆
I wouldn't recommend talking to him.
《すんなり
合格するためにはね》
Not if you want to pass the exam.
(紫)⦅ちょっと
トイレ行ってくる⦆
I gotta hit the restroom.
Don't talk to him?
《話しかけるなって…
そりゃねぇよ 紫さん》
That won't do, Murasaki...
《むしろ 一番に挨拶するべき
人じゃねぇのか!?》
I'd say it's very important that I introduce myself.
I'm heading over.
《俺は行くぜ》
《誰かから逃げたままで
宇宙飛行士になれると思うな》
I'll never become an astronaut by running from people!
《ビビることはない！
俺は もうすでに…➡
There's no need to be afraid...
I've already
一度 死んでいる》
died once.
《あれ以上の何が
起きるっていうんだ…！》
It can't get any worse.
《よし ズバッと言ってやる！》
Okay, I'm going to talk to him.
《うわっ…
バカか!?南波六太！》
Are you stupid, Nanba Mutta?!
はじめまして 南波六太です！
Nice to meet you! I'm Nanba Mutta.
Thank you for taking good care of my little brother, Hibito.
弟の日々人が いつもお世話になり
ありがとうございます！
I look forward to working with you!
今後とも どうぞ
よろしくお願い申し上げます！
《年賀状か…‼》
Are you writing a New Year's card?
別に 世話なんてしてないよ｡
I'm not too familiar with your brother.
あ…そうなんですか…｡
Oh, I see.
《終わった…日々人をネタに
会話を広げるはずが…》
I'm finished...
My plan was to use Hibito as a conversation starter.
But I was deflected...
《あっさりと はね返された！》
My angle of approach was too shallow.
《突入角度が浅すぎた！》
《どうしよ…》
What should I do?
(吾妻)一つだけ…➡
One question...
一つだけ答えてくれ｡
I have one question for you.
死ぬ覚悟はあるか？
Are you prepared to die?
《死ぬ覚悟…!?》
Prepared to die?
当然！覚悟はありますとも！
You bet!
I'm totally prepared!
そうか…｡
I see.
ビール飲むか？
Would you like some more beer?
あ はいっ…｡
Oh, yes...
I'm sorry.
すみません｡
ウソつきました｡
I was lying.
To be honest,
本当は…死ぬ覚悟…➡
I'm really not...
できてないです｡
prepared to die.
ねぇねぇねぇ お父さん｡➡
Look, dear!
フロリダに着いたらさぁ まず
ディズニーランド行くでしょお？
Once we get to Florida, we should start with Disneyland!
で 夜はデキシークロスロードに
行ってぇ～➡
At night, we can go to Dixie Crossroads and watch manatees while eating lobster and rock shrimp.
マナティ見ながらロブスターとか
ロックシュリンプ食べて➡
あと キーライム食べて…｡
And have some Key limes, too!
うどんでいいよ うどんで｡
I'd rather have udon.
(北村)…でしょ？
(せりか)そうかも｡
Right?
Probably...
⦅本当は…死ぬ覚悟…
できてません⦆
To be honest,
I'm really not...
prepared to die.
⦅たぶん｢こりゃもう死ぬな｣って
瞬間が来たとしても➡
If I find myself in a situation where I'm facing death,
ギリギリまで生きたいと
思いそうです⦆
I'll probably try whatever I can to survive.
⦅ブライアン…｡宇宙飛行士として
プライドのない➡
Brian,
my answer may be shameful for an astronaut,
答えかもしれませんが
死ぬ覚悟はありません｡➡
but I'm not prepared to die.
考えるなら
生きることを考えます⦆
Given a choice, I would choose life.
⦅そうか｡➡
Is that so?
それでいいぞ アズマ⦆
That's just fine, Azuma!
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅たいていの宇宙飛行士は
ＹＥＳと答えるけどな➡
Most astronauts will answer "yes".
But those are just words.
くち
口じゃ何とでも言える
薄っぺらいＹＥＳだ｡➡
That "yes" means nothing.
死ぬ覚悟なんていらねぇぞ｡
必要なのは｢生きる覚悟｣だ⦆
You shouldn't be prepared to die.
You should be prepared to live.
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅ＮＯと言える奴がいたら
そいつは信じていい⦆
If someone replies "no", you can trust them.
⦅死ぬ覚悟ですか…？⦆
Am I prepared to die?
⦅全くないです⦆
Absolutely not.
(吾妻)《兄弟だな…》
They're brothers...
(ﾏﾃﾗｯﾂｨ)ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
Zidane ejected for headbutting Materazzi
あ～あ➡
テレビもラジオも新聞も
ジダン ジダン ジダン ジダン➡
Zidane's on TV, Zidane's on the radio, Zidane's in the newspaper...
Zidane is everywhere.
ジダン一色だ 全く！
なんかそのやられた人➡
The guy he headbutted looks sort of happy.
ちょっと嬉しそう｡
学校で真似しちゃダメよ
あんた達｡➡
Don't try to imitate him, boys.
はや
流行りそうで怖いわ｡
しないよ｡
I'm worried this will catch on.
It won't.
逆にやられる可能性があるからな｡
It's possible someone could try it on you.
胸に鉄板仕込んどけ｡
Wear a metal plate beneath your shirts.
ていうか どこにも
アレが載ってないぞ｡なんでだ!?
Anyway, there isn't a single article about it.
Why not?!
We've tried everywhere.
ぜんめつ
全滅だな｡
あんなにはっきり見たのに…｡
It was impossible to miss...
世の中は ジダンに夢中で
見逃したんだな｡
The world was too focused on Zidane.
あのＵＦＯみたいのを｡
So they missed the UFO.
学校で みんなに聞いてみよっ｡
他に誰か見てるかも｡
おう｡
We can ask kids at school.
Maybe someone else saw it.
Yeah!
＜と 思っていたが…➡
That was our assumption.
あれを見たのは
私と日々人 ２人だけだった＞
But Hibito and I were the only ones who saw it.
は～ だ～れも信じてくれね～よ｡
No one believed me!
Same here. They kept wanting proof.
こっちも｡証拠見せろってさ｡
証拠つってもなぁ～｡
We don't have any...
今晩から裏の高台で見張ろうぜ！
ムッちゃん｡
Let's camp out on the hill tonight, Mu!
また出てくるかもしれんからさ｡
It could show up again.
父ちゃん！あれ貸して！
あれ～…ビデオカメラ！
Dad, can I borrow that...
That video camera?
ＵＦＯ撮ってくる｡
ふ～ん そうか 頑張れ｡
We're gonna film UFOs.
Oh, that's nice.
Good luck.
After that, Hibito and I spent the next three months...
＜私と日々人は
この日から実に３ヶ月以上も＞
Okay, the angle is perfect!
よし！バッチシこの角度｡
＜ＵＦＯを撮るため
あの裏の高台に通った…＞
...visiting the hill, waiting for our chance to film a UFO.
＜そして この日から
およそ３ヶ月後…＞
And three months later,
現在
＜私は日々人から１枚の
録画ディスクを受け取った＞
Hibito sent me a DVD.
＜2006年１０月２８日｡
ドーハのきせき➡
"October 28, 2006. Miracle of Doha.
さつえい南波日々人＞
Filmed by Nanba Hibito."
＜このＤＶＤ－Ｒに まさか
あんなもんが映ってるとはな＞
I didn't expect this DVD-R to show that...
Mutta, you hold Apo.
(母)六太 あんたがアポちゃんを
抱っこしときなさい｡
面倒なら連れて来なきゃいいのに｡
アポちゃんだって➡
If you didn't want to hold him, you shouldn't have brought him.
I'm sure that Apo wants to watch Hibito's launch.
日々人の打ち上げが
見たいに決まってるでしょ｡
アポちゃんって言うんですか？
His name is Apo?
かわいいですねぇ～！フフフ…！
He's so cute...
《あっ！…そうか！
この手があったか！》
R-Right, that's brilliant!
《いいぞアポ こいつは使える！》
Nice, Apo... Making yourself useful!
《すげぇ 肉球触ってる～》
Wow... She's feeling his paw.
Let's go, Mutta.
(父)行くぞ 六太～｡
(母)うわ～！バスよ バス！
Look! It's the bus!
(父)バス来たぞ バス｡
《ちっ…》
The bus is here.
じゃあみんな また後ほど｡
Well, I'll see you guys later.
行ってらっしゃ～い｡
(ケンジ)日々人君によろしく｡
Have fun!
Tell Hibito we said hi!
Welcome, CES-51 family members.
セス
ようこそ ＣＥＳ－５１クルーの
家族のみなさん！➡
今日 みなさんを ご案内するのは
私 宇宙飛行士のローリーです｡➡
I will be your guide today,
astronaut Lowry.
よろしく｡
It's a pleasure.
ヘーイ！ムッタ！
ゴブサタデース！
Hey, Mutta!
Long time, no see!
《ローリーがガイドか》
So Lowry's our guide.
ケネディ宇宙センターって
広いわね お父さん｡➡
Kennedy Space Center is huge, dear.
東京ディズニーランドが
1111個も入るんだって｡
You can fit 1,111 Tokyo Disney Lands inside!
へぇ｡ディズニーシーなら何個だ？
(母)それは載ってない｡
How many DisneySeas could fit?
It doesn't say.
この敷地内には ハクトウワシの
巣が いっぱいあって➡
The premises house many bald eagle nests, along with a bunch of crocodiles!
ワニもウジャウジャいるんだって｡
ウジャウジャってのは
何匹から ウジャウジャなんだ？
How many crocodiles do you need to have a bunch?
(母)それも載ってない｡
It doesn't say that, either.
そろそろですよ みなさん｡
It's almost time, everyone.
(クルー)報道の方
もう少し 下がって！
Could all journalists please step back?
Here they come!
(リンダの父)来た！
《くっそ～
格好いいなぁ チキショー》
Damn, that was cool...
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝの妻)いよいよね ダミアン｡
It's finally happening, Damian.
Yeah.
Daddy!
(バディ)月の石を持って帰るよ｡
I'll bring a moon rock back for you.
Okay!
(リンダ)行ってきます パパ｡
気をつけてな リンダ｡
I'm going to space, Dad.
Be careful, Linda.
キャー！日々人～！久しぶり～！
Hibito! It's been forever!
元気にしてたか？
Are you doing well?
Yeah.
Wow, you look so manly now...
あらまぁ たくましくなってぇ！
モテるでしょう？ねぇ ねぇ！
You must be popular with the girls.
この後みんな どうすんの？
決まってるじゃない！➡
What do you plan to do next?
That should be obvious!
We're going to Disney World.
ディズニーワールドに行くわよ！
なんとかマウンテン｡
Something Mountain.
(母)違うわよ！お父さん｡
スペースなんとかよ～｡
ウホン！
That's not it, Dad. It's Space Something...
おおっ アポも来てくれたのか｡
サンキュー｡
Even Apo's here?
Thanks.
みんなの言うこと
ちゃんときけよ アポ｡
Be a good boy, Apo.
Oh, Apo's an angel, right?
(母)あら～ いい子よねぇ
アポちゃん！
Just like me.
ワン！
(父)バカ犬だ こりゃ｡
俺は アポの次か…｡
So, I come after Apo?
ふっ…決まってたろ？さっきの｡
That entrance was smooth, right?
いちいちカッコつけやがって｡
Yeah.
Why do you have to make a scene?
俺らと同じ飛行機で
来りゃいいものを｡
You could have shared a plane.
それじゃあ 絵にならねえじゃん｡
That wouldn't have been much of an entrance.
Hmm?
これを月へ持っていってくれ｡
中身は ただのＤＶＤ－Ｒだが➡
Take this to the moon for me.
There's a DVD-R inside.
俺にとっては大事なものだ｡
It's important to me.
ふ～ん｡ま いいけど｡
これ持ってって どうすんの？
Sure, okay.
What should I do with it?
月の基地にでも
置いて来てくれりゃいい｡
Just leave it in the base.
あ コピーはないからなくすなよ｡
There aren't any copies, so don't lose it.
大事なのに
なんで置いて来るんだよ？
Why would you want me to leave something so important there?
フッ…決まってるだろ｡
Isn't that obvious?
数年後に必ず自分の手で
持って帰るためだ｡
In a few years,
I'll bring it back myself.
フッ…懐かしいな
まだ持ってたのか｡
This brings back memories...
He still had this thing?
ん!?日々人 なんだそれ｡
Hmm? What's that, Hibito?
ああ これね
すげぇもんが映ってんだ｡
Oh, this?
There's some amazing footage on it.
Eh?
My right hand spent its days afraid of losing something
but wished to be held by my left hand
I lead you by the hand
Is my hand only there to hold my own hand now?
I can't lose it
Amidst my nagging disappointment that I can do nothing
I felt I wanted to do something
I let go again
I'm not alone in this world
If my hands can only hold two things
then I hope one of them is you
Not alone, not alone
I want our hearts to be connected
I want to be connected
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#28 Miracle of Doha
＜１９９３年 １０月２８日｡➡
On October 28, 1993,
サッカー日本代表は
あとちょっとのところで➡
at the very last second, Japan lost their chance at a first World Cup appearance.
悲願のワールドカップ初出場を
逃してしまった＞
＜これ いわゆる｢ドーハの悲劇｣＞
This is known as the Agony of Doha.
As someone born on that day,
＜その日に生まれた私にとって
あのＤＶＤ－Ｒは 大事なものだ＞
that DVD-R is very important to me.
This brings back memories...
＜懐かしいな｡
ムッちゃん まだ持ってたのか＞
Mu still had this thing?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Miracle of Doha"
＜本当に強い奴ってのはな
手を出さないんだよ＞
Those who are truly strong don't fight back!
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
EVA outside the station!
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真で～す！
すっげぇ！
Awesome!